<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Education on Jorge Cimentada</title>
    <link>/tags/education/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Education on Jorge Cimentada</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 13 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="/tags/education/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Replicating Dupriez and Dumay (2006)</title>
      <link>/blog/2017-04-13-replicating-dupriez-and-dumay-2006/replicating-dupriez-and-dumay-2006/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2017-04-13-replicating-dupriez-and-dumay-2006/replicating-dupriez-and-dumay-2006/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;So, I was bored for two days and decided I’d replicate a paper I had read. The paper is called ‘Inequalities in school systems: effect of school structure or of society structure?’ written by Vincent Dupriez and Xavier Dumay which you can read from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/03050060600628074?scroll=top&amp;amp;needAccess=true&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. I made available two version, one in &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/cimentadaj/Inequality_schools_replication/raw/master/replication_tracking_pisa.pdf&#34;&gt;pdf&lt;/a&gt; and another in &lt;a href=&#34;https://cimentadaj.github.io/Inequality_schools_replication/replication_tracking_pisa.html&#34;&gt;html&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’re interested in looking at the code or suggesting some changes, do send me an email at &lt;code&gt;cimentadaj@gmail.com&lt;/code&gt; or check the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/cimentadaj/Inequality_schools_replication&#34;&gt;Github repository&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Los pobres no son los peores pero los ricos sí son los mejores: desigualdad educativa</title>
      <link>/blog/2016-09-24-los-pobres-no-son-los-peores-pero-los-ricos-s%C3%AD-son-los-mejores/los-pobres-no-son-los-peores-pero-los-ricos-s%C3%AD-son-los-mejores-desigualdad-educativa/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2016-09-24-los-pobres-no-son-los-peores-pero-los-ricos-s%C3%AD-son-los-mejores/los-pobres-no-son-los-peores-pero-los-ricos-s%C3%AD-son-los-mejores-desigualdad-educativa/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Hace poco escribí un artículo sobre la desigualdad educativa en países Latinoamericanos y describí como la República Dominicana no parece estar tan mal como creemos. Ofrecí dos posibles explicaciones de porque esto pudiera ser bueno o malo, dependiendo del enfoque con que se ve (missing link after the ‘,’ with this: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jorgecimentada.com/?p=137&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;http://www.jorgecimentada.com/?p=137&lt;/a&gt;). Luego de escribirlo me quedé pensando en algo que di por sentado: ¿realmente los ‘peores’ estudiantes son los estudiantes pobres? ¿son los estudiantes pobres los ‘peores’ en las escuelas públicas y privadas? Y a raíz del artículo de &lt;a href=&#34;http://acento.com.do/2016/opinion/8377420-desigualdad-educativa-interpela-desafia/&#34;&gt;Dinorah Garcia&lt;/a&gt;, ¿existe desigualdad entre las zonas rurales y urbanas?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Estas preguntas no solo ayudan a diagnosticar el estado actual de la desigualdad, más que eso, permiten inferir de donde pudieran provenir las fuentes de desigualdad. Si encontramos una diferencia bastante amplia entre los ‘mejores’ y ‘peores’ estudiantes, pero la diferencia es menor entre escuelas públicas y privada, pues la causa no es necesariamente las diferencias en calidad entre las tipos de escuelas. Sin embargo, si existen diferencias similares entre los estudiantes de escuelas rurales y urbanas, pues la razón puede ser precisamente en temas como la calidad educativa entre sectores pobres y ricos. Lo interesante de estas preguntas es que son todas preguntas empíricas, y se pueden responder con bases de datos como las de TERCE.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;realmente-los-peores-estudiantes-son-los-estudiantes-pobres&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;1. ¿realmente los ‘peores’ estudiantes son los estudiantes pobres?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;!-- ![1stplot](img/inquality_grade_topic.png) --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;img/inquality_grade_topic.png&#34; alt=&#34;Drawing&#34; style=&#34;width: 600px;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Este gráfico presente claramente que no lo son. Tanto en matemáticas y lenguaje, los estudiantes más pobres (barra azul) suelen tener una mejor puntuación que los ‘peores’ estudiantes (barra roja). Esto parecer ser el caso sin importar que sean de la zona rural o urbana. Sería informativo comparar estos resultados desagregados por tipo de escuela, es decir, privada o pública, para identificar si los ‘peores’ estudiantes son los de las escuelas públicas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;En contraste, los estudiantes ricos (barra morada) si tienen la misma puntuación que los ‘mejores’ estudiantes (barra verde). De hecho, en zonas rurales los estudiantes ricos se desempeñan tan bien que obtienen una puntuación más alta que los ‘mejores’ estudiantes. Este gráfico cuenta una historia muy interesante. En resumen, los estudiantes pobres no reflejan ser los ‘peores’ del sistema educativo. Y por otro lado, los estudiantes ricos sí son los mejores estudiantes en sus respectivas materias.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Desde un punto de vista más general, la distribución entre la zona rural y urbana es muy similar, sugiriendo que no existe una desigualdad muy marcada.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;son-los-estudiantes-pobres-los-peores-en-las-escuelas-publicas-y-privadas&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;2. ¿son los estudiantes pobres los ‘peores’ en las escuelas públicas y privadas?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;!-- ![2ndplot](img/inquality_public_topic.png) --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;img/inquality_public_topic.png&#34; alt=&#34;Drawing&#34; style=&#34;width: 650px;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;En este gráfico el panorama es un poco diferente. Los estudiantes pobres (barra verde) sí se desempeñan peor que los estudiantes promedios (barra roja) en las escuelas privadas. Esto no significa que son los ‘peores’ ya que el punto de comparación es el estudiante promedio y no los ‘peores’ estudiantes de las escuelas privadas. No obstante, si se nota una estratificación bastante clara: los estudiantes pobres tienen puntuación más baja que los estudiantes promedio, mientras que los estudiantes ricos (barra azul) tienen mayor puntuación que el estudiante average.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Viendo la otra cara de la moneda, las escuelas públicas, los estudiantes pobres si tienen el mismo desempeño que el estudiante promedio. Esto no significa que han mejorado en comparación con la escuela privada. Todo lo contrario. Los estudiantes pobres tienen un desempeño similar tanto en las escuelas públicas y privadas; lo que pasa es que el estudiante promedio de la escuela pública (barra roja) tienen una puntuación mucho más baja que el mismo estudiante en la escuela privada. Esto sugiere que, en promedio, los estudiantes de escuelas públicas tienen un peor desempeño que los de las escuelas privadas. De hecho, los ricos son igual de buenos sin importar el tipo de escuela. Los pobres, por otro lado, tienen una puntuación similar entre escuelas públicas y privadas, pero tienen un desempeño ligeramente menor en las escuelas públicas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;existe-desigualdad-entre-las-zonas-rurales-y-urbanas&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;3. ¿existe desigualdad entre las zonas rurales y urbanas?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;!-- ![3rdplot](img/inquality_ruralidad_topic.png) --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;img/inquality_ruralidad_topic.png&#34; alt=&#34;Drawing&#34; style=&#34;width: 650px;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Este gráfico presenta que tanta desigualdad existe entre los estudiantes en 3ro y 6to de primaria en matemática y lengua para las zonas rurales y urbanas. Empecemos con la lengua española, la sección con las puntuaciones en color rojo. Para los estudiantes de 3ro de primaria, resulta que hay una desigualdad mucho más grande en la zona urbana que en la zona rural. Pero esta desigualdad es en gran parte debido a que los ‘mejores’ estudiantes de la zona urbana son mucho mejor que los de la zona rural, mientras que los ‘peores’ estudiantes son prácticamente iguales. ¿Será este el efecto escuela privada? Para 6to de primaria la desigualdad se ha doblado entre ambas zonas. Esto es consistente con la teoría de capital humano propuesta por James Heckman, que sugiere que mientras más pasa el tiempo, más difícil se hace cerrar la brecha entre los ‘mejores’ y ‘peores’ estudiantes. Aquí se nota la gran brecha que existe entre las zonas urbanas y zonas rurales. En la sección de matemáticas (puntuaciones en color azul), la diferencia entre la zona rural y urbana es más pequeña, aunque se nota un patron claro: los estudiantes urbanos son mejores que los rurales. Cualquier persona que &lt;a href=&#34;http://linkis.com/www.listindiario.com/AG90F&#34;&gt;sabe los pocos recursos que se le asignan a las provincias fuera de Santiago y Santo Domingo&lt;/a&gt; no se sorprendería en encontrar estos resultados. No obstante, siempre es bueno confirmar las especulaciones con datos empíricos.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;que-significa-todo-esto&#34; class=&#34;section level4&#34;&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;¿Que significa todo esto?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Realmente, toda la información presentada aquí es pura descripción. No podemos concluir que vivir en las zonas rurales o ir a una escuela pública hace que tengas un peor desempeño, por más que quisiera. La ciencia no funciona de esta manera. Aparentemente existen brechas importantes entre las zonas urbanas y rurales, y tal y como sugiere Ceara Hatton, la distribución del presupuesto nacional abarca en su mayoría a Santo Domingo y Santiago. Se podría empezar por priorizar el gasto educativo a los que más lo necesitan, que suelen ser las zonas rurales. Esto tampoco es una solución inmediata; hay que priorizar la calidad del gasto y no el monto.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Por otro lado, podemos ver que los estudiantes pobres si tienen un peor desempeño que los estudiantes ricos, tanto en las escuelas privadas como en las públicas. Sugerir que se debe mejorar la calidad educativa pública ya se sabe, y si esta fuera homogénea a lo largo de las escuelas esperaríamos que los estudiantes ricos tuvieran la misma puntuación que los pobres, algo que no es el caso. Me parece que una de las explicaciones puede estar en el hecho de que los pobres tienen una ‘racha’ o acumulación de malas experiencias educativas a lo largo de la vida. Al momento de llegar a 3ro o 6to de primaria ya están muy por detrás de sus compañeros de mayores recursos. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.diariolibre.com/opinion/dialogo-libre/el-problema-es-que-la-economia-crece-pero-no-se-distribuye-la-riqueza-EE5262978&#34;&gt;El acceso a educación temprana, de muy alta calidad, de forma universal, puede ayudar a remediar este problema de inmovilidad social&lt;/a&gt;. Esto es algo que muchas personas ya han pedido en otros países y no es nuevo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Para terminar en una nota buena, no nos debemos sentir tan mal por estos resultados: como dije aquí(poner link &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jorgecimentada.com/?p=137&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;http://www.jorgecimentada.com/?p=137&lt;/a&gt;), en comparación con cualquier otro país latinoamericano, tenemos mucha menor desigualdad, lo importante sería asegurarnos que no crezca, porque es muy difícil cerrarlo después.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Notas:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;La pobreza en este caso se mide como los estudiantes que vienen de familias donde sus padres no se graduaron de la escuela secundaria. Opuestamente, los ricos son los estudiantes que vienen de familias donde los padres han obtenido un grado universitario o más.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;El promedio de los ‘peores’ estudiantes es el promedio de todos los niños que están en el 25% de la parte inferior de la distribución, mientras que el promedio de los ‘mejores’ estudiantes es el promedio del 25% de la parte superior de la distribución.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cualquier persona interesada en reproducir estos análisis, &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/cimentadaj/blog-articles/tree/master/private_public_schools&#34;&gt;aquí&lt;/a&gt; está el código&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Children: public or private goods?</title>
      <link>/blog/2016-08-29-children-public-or-private-goods/children-public-or-private-goods/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Aug 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2016-08-29-children-public-or-private-goods/children-public-or-private-goods/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The role of the welfare state, as agreed by many scholars, is to de-commodify its citizens. Some argue that this should be the way that the generosity of the state should be measured; instead of net public and private social expenditure, it should be the extent to which citizens are de-commodified by the services and transfers of the welfare state.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The aim of educational investment can be seen from different lenses, but today we’ll focus on the economic and social returns to education. An important share of the state budget is aimed at the formation and education of citizens through public education. In countries where there is a substantial investment, human capital, innovation and production are maximized creating a highly productive working population that can sustain the young and the elderly through pensions, health and child care; note that in some scenarios an uneducated workforce can sustain those who depend on them but it will possible be with more quantity of work (hours) and less quality [1]. Following this logic, it is arguable that because most of today’s workers will benefit from pensions, retirement schemes, care assistance and healthcare, they are to take care of their young population, the next generation’s workers. Covering kids’ education through higher taxes could be seen as loan: A young worker covers the expenses of a child, and that child, eventually, will cover the pension of that worker; this is a simplified version of the argument.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The scheme I just outlined is virtually widespread across western European countries. But it is important to note that in other countries, due to the intrinsic organization of the state, it is unimaginable to do so. In the counterfactual situation where you don’t have a strong welfare state, maybe it’s unfair to tax those who are not benefiting from the goods that the taxes are being spent on. In places like the United States, where the generosity of the welfare system is minimal, some people don’t find it reasonable to pay for everyone’s kids, even more, when you’re paying already, for instance, a private school for your own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s also another important case: childless couples. Perhaps the exact reason why they didn’t have children was not to have to spend a big proportion of their lifelong income. So, why should they pay? According to their position it seems very unfair. Their long held argument can be synthesized in one sentence: those who want children should be the ones who pay for them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After presenting very briefly the arguments of the positions in the debate, it is interesting then to posit the important question concerning it: Should children be a public or private good? I presume this question is easy to answer but not easy to apply; adjusting a state to this premise can take decades and it’s an expensive endeavor. So, evaluating this question must be accompanied by hard scientific thinking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will start off by stating my position on this dilemma. I support the notion of kids being a public good. I support it not just for the fact that they will pay or not for my pension schemes but because everyone deserves the same opportunities. And if we don’t provide them with equal opportunities, then the gap we see between poor and rich will be as it is today: very sizable. Despite that I sometimes question myself: can they entirely be a public good? Adopting the notion that the family is a private sphere, and at least the states considers it because it is reluctant to interfere within it, then children should not just be considered as a public good. If we pay attention to authors like McDonald (2000) and Lewis &amp;amp; Astrom (1992), we constantly see that the way the state promotes gender equality in the family is not through hands-on, direct implementation of intrusive policies like reeducating couples and telling them what’s right and what’s not. Instead, most of the family policies try to promote gender equality by integrating women into the labor force, reducing the gender wage gap and promoting female and male parental leave. Kids then can never be entirely public goods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, do they contribute to society, meaning, are the interrelated with the “public”?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think this question is rooted in the intrinsic dynamics of society. We are social animals and it is unfashionable to think that we are independent of each other. The most independent citizen living within society is never unattached of its surroundings. Everyone’s paths cross indirectly and directly with the decisions and actions of other people. It might be even irresponsible to think that one’s actions only affect themselves. The principal idea to take from this question is that those who think of themselves as independent actors of society are committing a fallacy that could be the exact reason why the levels and indexes of inequalities are so high nowadays.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Nobel laureate James Heckman has been arguing for the past decade one of his most controversial findings: the first years of a child are the most important ones. Contrary to the long held thought of concentrating the bigger part of the educational budget on tertiary education, he finds that the return of investment of human beings are the highest in the early years and it decreases with time. This means that the first years should be the ones where the highest investment should be: be it monetary and emotional. With the evaluation of the Perry preschool program and the Abecedarian project, Heckman finds that you can trace inequalities between children as early as 22 months old. The principal reason being that some kids get better early childhood education than others. Among others, I think this an important reason to reflect why children should be a public good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Inequalities are being reproduced from an early age, leading to a more polarized society where you have lucky and unlucky kids. Those that receive the better education will at the end, have better jobs, less odds of committing crime, more prone of a stable union (possibly due to the fact that they will have a stable job). Furthermore, and I think this is a key argument against those that don’t want to contribute, these educated children will in most of the cases, help society better than the ones who aren’t educated. This help can be manifested in direct and indirect ways: respecting traffic lights, avoiding corruption in public institutions, being fair, meritocratic, reporting robberies, not stealing, respecting others, among an endless number of thing. This point makes an important argument: the focus on which some of the parents and scholars are viewing the debate might be wrongly specified. As I have succinctly showed, the benefits of having an educated population are not only personal, but also public. I think that the principal reason why there is a strong opposition to this idea is because they evaluate it as taking care of someone else’s children when nobody is taking care of theirs; that is a strong point, but I urge everyone to see it with another lense. If you turned the coin around and you start seeing this as an investment towards societal problems, which in the short and long run affects us all, then it becomes a tax deduction, just as any other one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I argued before, we are all interrelated and it is our business what our fellow citizens do. So, someone who doesn’t have children, still participates in society, interacts within it, and is affected by criminality, public services, and private services. The problem with providing this argument for a country with a weak welfare state is that you won’t receive quality elderly care from this children when you retire. Conversely, in strong-welfare countries, the argument is the main (pragmatic) reason to do so. However, the second idea, that we should do it for everyone to have the same opportunities, is more than enough to warrant the changes. This would be an even more noble reason because you won’t be contributing to receive something but because everyone deserves the same opportunities. For the U.S, this is a reason to tackle one of the most debatable topics of the last 40 years: inequalities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, if we were to delve more into the inequality problem, which shows itself to be the major issue when comparing educational opportunities, it is also important to think of the struggles of having children. Not particularly of the difficulties of childrearing, which are a consequence of the decision to child bear, but the fact that it is too hard to combine work and childrearing now a days. This is quite notorious in the lean welfare state countries and southern European ones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The demands of the work space and the schedules that are imposed to parents and workers make it virtually impossible for men or women to dedicated high quality time to their children. The most common solution that we’ve seen is for women to quit their jobs or to sacrifice leisure time to take care of the child. So, in the end, this deems either the education of the future population or the ambitions and life course perspective of a mother.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Catherine Hakim’s preference theory, posits that women now have the preference of having a child but this was not entirely the case in the past where the bargaining power of the man was higher than hers. But a woman who has professional ambitions might also want to have a baby. Does this mean that she has to renounce her ambitions? This will certainly harm the tax system (less taxes paid) but it will help society because she will dedicate more time to the child (And if you acknowledge this, then you are implicitly arguing that children are indeed a public good). But as one of Esping-Andersen’s chapter from his book the Incomplete Revolution shows, permitting the woman to go back to work after parental leave, by providing free high quality childcare, will in the long run pay the costs of this childcare service and even produce a surplus for the welfare state. And that is why I think this is not an easy question to answer, conversely to what Paula England and Nancy Folbre imply. The implication of implementing this idea entails a complete reorganization and readjustment of the tax and welfare system, if there is one [2]. And also, what would be the consequences of this new regime besides the public childcare? Will the problem of inequalities be solved or others problems will arise as side effects?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And here I will talk about something that is intrinsically related to having healthy children: the labor perspectives of the mother. The Incomplete Revolution, book by Esping-Andersen, takes on the job of explaining the problem with many of today’s countries: the poor family policies that they implement (if any) when concerning women’s labor market inclusion and combination of working and childrearing. Specifically in two chapters he argues that children should be a public good because children benefit everyone, but furthermore, an important step is to include women in the labor market given that it will help the income prospects of the household and the egalitarianism in the family. How can this be related to children as being a public good, one may ask? This is a complex relation, on which everything is potentially endogenous, but all present evidence shows that if the mother goes back to work after the parental leave, it does not have an adverse effect on the development of the child. This is, assuming that the child is in early high quality childcare. This has important implications! It means that the inclusion of mothers into the labor force will increase the bargaining power of the women in the family, it will heighten the income of the family household, it will expand the human capital of the women; in short, it will not impose the opportunity costs that she will otherwise would’ve had to bear for the remaining part of her life if she would’ve stayed home. This will increase the chances of being in a more egalitarian family, thus the children will be exposed to more equal surroundings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the point of view that I see it, it’s about heightening the bar of educational attainment. Instead of having the two extremes that we see in the liberal welfare state regimes (excluding UK), extremely poor and uneducated groups and highly rich and educated group, you will set a bar of minimum education. By doing this you will inevitable give secureness to families, opportunities, possibly change the economic structure of the country by increasing the odds of turning it to a knowledge based economy (although this is way more complex then I suggest).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a conclusion, I shall finish off with another question, which I think is as important as the one which initiated this essay. I have tried to argue that children are faring under the destiny that is imposed to them. There has been, since after the World War II, persistent inequalities between classes and all the evidence shows that they are not shrinking. In some countries, namely European ones, the decision to help children might be an economic one or an altruistic one. This is worrisome. Are children being taken care of in Europe because they are the payers of the pensioners or because of the noble argument of equal opportunities? I really don’t know the reason for which Europe or the U.S is doing it for. But should everyone take care of children for the economic benefits or for the equal opportunity argument?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[1] Let’s not get into the major changes that the quality of job production will have if the population is highly educated. For a book with interesting ideas, read The Race between Education and Technology by Claudia Goldin &amp;amp; Lawrence Katz.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[2] In the case where there is no welfare state, then this is another story.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
